<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://tarun360.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://tarun360.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2023-10-17T18:39:18+00:00</updated><id>https://tarun360.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Beginning of infinity</title><link href="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/beg-inf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beginning of infinity" /><published>2023-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/beg-inf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/beg-inf/"><![CDATA[<p>On July 19th, 2023, there was a big meeting at D. E. Shaw’s office in India, where I work as a software engineer. The purpose of the meeting was to bring together important leaders from the New York and Hyderabad offices to talk about the company’s future plans, challenges, and strategies. Something really interesting happened during the meeting when a top boss unexpectedly said, “We might run out of ideas.” This got me thinking because it pointed out a big risk and showed how important it is to always come up with new and creative trading strategies, especially as the old ones become less effective over time.</p>

<p>Is it possible to continuously improve trading strategies and continue to generate profits indefinitely? There is a somewhat reasonable argument suggesting that all trading strategies employed by various firms would strive for maximum efficiency, leading to a potential state of equilibrium where further optimization becomes unlikely. In this hypothetical scenario, all trading strategies across firms would reach an equilibrium, efficient state, making further improvement seemingly impossible.</p>

<p>This is where David Deutch’s mind-bending book, “Beginning of Infinity,” presents a compelling argument favouring infinite progress, from which one could infer the continuous improvement of trading algorithms. The book asserts that as long as error correction mechanisms are integrated into a system (as is inherent in trading markets), the system can infinitely self-improve. It posits that anything allowed by the physical laws of nature can be achieved through the continual generation of knowledge and error-correcting mechanisms.</p>

<p>Getting the full grasp of this never-ending progress notion needs more than a quick summary. That’s why I enthusiastically encourage diving into “Beginning of Infinity.” This book stands as the most impactful read in my life thus far.</p>

<p>The title, “Beginning of Infinity,” is really interesting: Within an infinite set of whole numbers, any number you select (e.g., 10<sup>82</sup> ≈ the number of atoms in the universe) will always be <i>unusually</i> close to 0 (i.e., the beginning). Hence, in the grand scheme of infinity, we are always at the beginning – beginning of infinity – always.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="psych" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A case for beginning of infinity at D. E. Shaw]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You and your research/work/career</title><link href="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/you-and-your-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You and your research/work/career" /><published>2023-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/you-and-your-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/you-and-your-research/"><![CDATA[<p>The ‘You and Your Research’ talk by Dr. Richard Hamming is a fantastic discussion applicable to careers in any field. One can watch it on YouTube <a href="https://youtu.be/a1zDuOPkMSw?si=K07WoHnMhQ8Nm1fR">here</a>. Dr. Hamming imparts great advice on envisioning your research or career and leading a purposeful life. Here I would like to share my thoughts on two specific ideas mentioned in this talk:</p>

<p><i>“If what you are working on is not important, and it’s not likely to lead to important things, then why are you working on it?”</i></p>

<p>This statement, and similar ideas about ‘meaningful work’, always make me ponder — what work should I really do? I certainly admit that my current software engineering job doesn’t quite measure up to the level of ‘meaningful work’ like drug discovery or rocket building. However, I console myself with the belief that I am building useful skills, preparing for a future where I can engage in work with tangible societal impact, rather than just making some enterprise messaging tool 10% faster. I have engaged in research during my undergrad, and while I am super proud of the work I have done, it’s certainly not in the top 1% category, far from it. Lately, I have been striving to make more meaningful contributions. For instance, I recently read a compelling paper about changing the incentive structure of social media platforms to combat fake news. The paper provided very practical, gamified solutions. After reading it, I had some ideas on how to extend it, and I emailed the authors with my thoughts. Well, that’s something. After all, ideas have infinite reach.</p>

<p><i>“Study your successes closely”</i></p>

<p>We often hear about learning from failures, but this was probably the first time I contemplated learning from successes. I recently experienced a kind of success, if one could call it that. I had spent 3-4 months tirelessly trying to secure a collaboration opportunity with an early-stage AI startup — countless hours (and headaches due to screen brightness) spent scraping sites like Y Combinator and LinkedIn to connect with early-stage AI startups. Didn’t get any success and eventually left it. A month after giving it a rest, a startup co-founder reached out to me with the opportunity I was seeking. It was quite serendipitous. This happened because during my previous search, I had interacted with a post on AI startups, and this co-founder found my profile through that interaction. It’s remarkable how, by reaching out and creating some entropy, one can potentially create luck for oneself. This was one of the motivations for sending the email mentioned above.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="work" /><category term="work" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts from the famous talk "You and your research"]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Provisional existence as a software engineer</title><link href="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/provisional-existence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Provisional existence as a software engineer" /><published>2023-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/provisional-existence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://tarun360.github.io/blog/2023/provisional-existence/"><![CDATA[<p>Sometime back I came across the quote “The days are long, but the years are short” by Gretchen Rubin and it immediately struck a chord with me. I checked its origin and found that it’s a parent adage implying that children grow up fast. But for me it somehow reminded me of my daily life as a software engineer. The days are long – meetings, debugging, some coding, and some more debugging. That stupid bug takes forever to fix, seemingly the most important thing in my life at the moment, but a week later I can’t even remember what it was.</p>

<p>Few months later, on re-reading the book <i>Man’s Search For Meaning</i> by Victor E. Frankl, I was drawn upon the idea of “provisional existence” – A man who is not able to see the end of his “provisional existence” ceases to have an ultimate aim in his life. The book mentions how Frankl’s fellow inmates in Germany’s concentration camps, having no idea when their liberation would happen, found their days longer than weeks. The book gives additional examples of how tuberculosis patients in a sanatorium having no fixed date of their release felt a similar phenomenon. I could relate this to my profession of software engineering at big tech companies. The daily tasks seem arduous and long, but the week goes by rather swiftly.</p>

<p>The entire promotion cycle within these big tech companies feels like a gamified and self-fulfilling endeavour. Moving from one level to another takes increasingly longer periods: approximately 1.5 years from L1 to L2, around 3 years from L2 to L3, then jumps of roughly 4 years, 6 years, and so on.The career growth is logarithmic; worse than linear. Stock options are structured in a way that there’s disproportionately more money in unvested stocks, incentivizing employees to stay longer; exemplifying the principle of loss aversion. Everything Is designed to keep individuals on the hedonic treadmill, with no discernible end date — just a perpetual cycle.</p>

<p>To be sure, software engineering is one of the cushiest jobs available right now in India, and I believe elsewhere as well. It offers excellent pay and favourable working conditions. The problem seems to me, as Victor Frankl puts it, means to live but no meaning. <a href="https://www.jointaro.com/question/PeIMgVaRQj8sToE44qqr/i-feel-destined-for-mediocrity-is-there-a-way-out/">This post</a> by a senior software engineer at Pinterest seems to be a common phenomenon. This is something which I actively notice in myself and my colleagues as well. People consciously or unconsciously try to combat it in different ways.</p>

<p>Some choose to slog longer hours in pursuit of additional responsibilities, finding meaning in mentoring or managing new employees. Others seek solace in luxurious experiences, dining at expensive restaurants or embarking on foreign vacations to Europe. Some distract themselves with video games like DOTA or CSGO. Then there are those who opt to switch careers, with product management being a popular choice, or venture into entrepreneurship.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><category term="psych" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Insights after working as a software engineer for 1 year.]]></summary></entry></feed>